Register to the Rossiĭskoe natsional'noe ob"edinenie records
Hoover Institution Archives
Rossiĭskoe natsional'noe ob"edinenie records
1929-1981
82066
Rossiĭskoe natsional'noe ob"edinenie
7 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box 4.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Russian émigré community in Belgium and other European countries over the time of the Russian Civil War, World War II, and cold war period includes correspondence, reports, minutes of meetings, printed and other material
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Historical Background
After the Bolsheviks seized power in 1917, Russia plunged into a bloody Civil War waged between the Red and White Armies. In the fall of 1920 the White Army was defeated, and some 100,000 demoralized White Army troops and 50,000 civilians boarded ships of the former Imperial Black Sea Fleet and fled the Crimea for Constantinople and exile. General Piotr Nikolaevich Vrangel, Chief Commander of the White Army in Crimea, negotiated with the Ottoman Empire and the French who occupied Constantinople at the end of the First World War for permission to settle the fully armed White Army in several camps in Turkey, Yugoslavia, and the Aegean island of Lemnos. The principal camp was at Gallipoli in Turkey. There General Vrangel prepared his army for a military campaign against the Bolshevik government.
By the year 1923 it became clear that the Bolsheviks had consolidated their control in Russia and hopes of a military campaign against them vanished. The White Army troops had to be reintegrated into civilian life. In 1924 Vrangel formed the Russian General Military Union (Russkii Obshche-Voinskii Soiuz). This organization preserved the army structure of the demilitarized White Army and played an important role in the very survival of military refugees. At the same time many regimental associations and societies of First World War and Civil War veterans started to form in émigré communities.
Historical Note
Russian National League was founded in 1948 due to the extremely difficult situation of the Russian émigré community and its desire to unify the majority of the Russian organizations in Belgium. The main purpose of the organization was the representation, unification and protection of Russian émigrés living in Belgium. It was based on unconditional devotion to Russia (not the USSR), loyalty to the national ideal, and adherence to Christian culture and civilization.
The organization supported a wide range of legal and social assistance to its members, established contact with all Russian national organizations inside and outside Belgium, provided assistance in founding a Russian Foreign National Center and supported all national-patriotic forces. It was not a political organization, because its main purpose was serving to their Motherland and preserving memory of the heroes of the White movement.
In 1964 the Russian National League initiated a celebration of the 1100th anniversary of the Russian State. It also commemorated the anniversary of the founding of Saint Petersburg, and organized various art and book exhibits, opera concerts, and other events in Brussels and provinces. It built a cathedral-monument to the martyred Russian Tsar and other victims of Bolshevism.
By resolution of the Russian National League Council of February 21, 1982, the existence of the Russian House and Library came to an end due to financial difficulties. The last information bulletin, Number 292, was issued in April 1982.
Scope and Content of Collection
Russian National League papers contain information about the activities of this organization and Russian émigré community in Belgium after World War II. Materials were divided into six series.
The Office Files document the history, statute, purpose and objectives of the organization. The papers show the connections between the Russian National League with the Russian Union (ROVS -Russkii Obshche-Voinskii Soiuz), formed by General Peter Vrangel in 1924, which played an important role in the survival of the military refugees. Scattered across the globe, often without property or a steady source income, many émigrés faced a life of poverty and destitution. They did not have easy access to government institutions, local charity organizations, or in family host countries. Correspondence file includes letters to the state and governmental officials regarding Russian émigrés and their needs, and to members of the Principal Headquarters of the Russian National League with discussion of the issues on the pages of Chasovoi magazine. The minutes of meetings of the Russian National League cover period 1948-1979. Of special interest in this collection are the testimonials on the kidnapping in Paris of Russian Generals Evgenii Miller and Aleksandr Kutepov. Oversize Materials contain fabric banners and advertisements about Russian book exhibits in Brussels.
The Publications File contains a collection of various émigré publications and monthly bulletins of Russian workers in Belgium. Vasilii Orekhov was the editor of Chasovoi magazine – the most prominent anti-Bolshevik émigré "white" magazine reflecting the ROVS position. In 1936 after the magazine openly supported General Francisco Franco in the Spanish Civil War, V. Orekhov was forced to relocate this publication from France to Belgium. After World War II Vasilii Orekhov founded the Russian National League and continued his publication of Chasovoi magazine and the monthly bulletin of Russian workers in Belgium.
The Radio Broadcasts include transcripts of the Russian section, Spanish radio, Madrid. At the time General Franco started his fight for liberation of Spain from communism, Soviet leaders initiated creation of international brigades and sent them to Spain. As a result, General Franco allowed Russian officers (from the Russian Imperial Army) to join the Spanish Army. Vasilii Orekhov started the first Russian émigré independent radio station in Spain.
Printed matter file includes newspapers, newspaper clippings, and scrapbooks covering period 1926-1980.
Cultural life depicts various art and book exhibits, opera performances, and reflects other events in Brussels and the provinces, connecting the materials in the collection with the events of the Russian émigré community in Belgium.
Photographs commemorate significant events in the life of the Russian émigré community abroad
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog
Subjects
Vooruzhennye Sily na IUge Rossii; Refugees; Russians-—Belgium; Russians in foreign countries; Soviet Union; Soviet Union—-History-—Revolution, 1917-1921—-Refugees; Soviet Union—-Social conditions; World War, 1914-1918
Related Material
David Davidovich Grimm papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Collection Contents
- Office file, 1920-1979. (Box 1)
  Correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, newsletters, and minutes of meetings, arranged by subject
  - General
    - Statute of the Organization, undated (Folder 1: 1)
    - Purpose and objectives of the organization, undated (Folder 1: 2)
    - Russian National League in Belgium, memorandum, undated (Folder 1: 3)
    - Glavnokomanduiushchii Vooruzhennymi Silami na IUge Rossii generala Vrangelia, prikaz O Zemle ot 25 maia 1920 goda (Order of General Vrangel, Commander in Chief of the Russian Army stationed in Southern Russia, 1920 May 25) (Folder 1: 4)
    - Russian émigrés killed while serving for the French Foreign Legion, list, 1921-1933 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Russkii Obshchevoinskii Soiuz, prikaz Generala Vrangelia number 35 ob obrazovanii (Order number 35 issued by General Peter Vrangel on formation of the Russian All Military Union), 1924 September 1 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Soiuz Gallipoliitsev vo Frantsii, Prikaz number 40 Predsedatelia (Order number 40 of the Chairman of the [Russian] Gallipoli Union in France), 1929 May 25 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Obshchestvo Gallipoliitsev, postanovlenie Soveta (Resolution of the Council of the Gallipoli Union), 1929 September 8 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Vasilii Orekhov, Chairman of the Russian National League in Belgium, membership cards, 1937-1959 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Appeals, declarations, leaflets, open letters, and resolutions (in Russian and French), 1942-1967 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Russian National League, list of members.
      Includes addresses
      - 1951-1952 (Folder 1: 11)
      - 1956 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Russian émigrés, reunion, Brussels, 1960 July 31 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1929-1978 (Folder 1: 14-15)
    - Chasovoi (Watchman) magazine editor's office, 1929-1956 (Folder 1: 16)
    - Correspondence regarding Russian émigrés and press (media), 1932-1977. (Folder 1: 17-20)
      Include letters from Russia
    - Official correspondence with state and governmental officials, 1937-1977 (Folder 1: 21-22)
    - Official correspondence with state and governmental officials, 1937-1977 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Chairman
      - General, 1937-1968; 1973 (Folder 2: 2-3)
      - Strictly confidential with the members of the Principal Headquarters of the Russian National League, 1956-1971 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Congress of the Russian National League, 1952 (Folder 2: 5-6)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - 1948 (Folder 2: 7)
    - 1949 (Folder 2: 8)
    - 1950 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1951
      - General (Folder 3: 2)
      - Material from the First Congress of the Russian National League, Brussels, 1951 April 15 (Folder 3: 3)
    - 1952 (Folder 3: 4-5)
    - 1953 (Folder 3: 6)
    - 1956
      - General (Folder 3: 7)
      - Second Congress of the Russian National League, 1956 September 13-16. (Folder 3: 8-9)
        Includes list of delegates, program, resolution, communiqué, and correspondence
      - Press release (Folder 3: 10)
    - 1957
      - General (Folder 3: 11)
      - Materials of the Congress on Rights and Freedom in Russia, Hague, 1957 April 25-27
        - General (Folder 3: 12)
        - Publications
          - Congrès pour l'instauration de la libertè et des droits en Russie, compte-rendu analytique. (Folder 3: 13)
          - Kongress Za prava i svobodu v Rossii, sbornik materialov Kongressa (Congress For the Rights and Freedom in Russia, compiled documents). (Folder 3: 14)
    - 1958 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 1959 (Folder 4: 2)
    - 1960 (Folder 4: 3)
    - 1961 (Folder 4: 4)
    - 1962 (Folder 4: 5)
    - 1963 (Folder 4: 6)
    - 1964 (Folder 4: 7)
    - 1965 (Folder 4: 8)
    - 1966 (Folder 4: 9)
    - 1967. (Folder 4: 10-11)
      Includes list of events (in Brussels and Paris) commemorating 50th anniversary of the victory of the Russian revolution, 1967. Includes extensive correspondence and minutes of meetings
    - 1968 (Folder 4: 12)
    - 1969 (Folder 4: 13)
    - 1970 (Folder 4: 14)
    - 1971 (Folder 4: 15)
    - 1972 (Folder 4: 16)
    - 1973 (Folder 4: 17)
    - 1974 (Folder 4: 18)
    - 1975 (Folder 4: 19)
    - 1977 (Folder 4: 20)
    - 1978 (Folder 4: 21)
    - 1979 (Folder 4: 22)
  - Reports for meetings, Mostly undated. (Folder 4: 23-24)
    Includes reports dated 1956 and 1970
  - Russian émigré community, materials on unification.
    - General, 1952-1979 (Folder 4: 25)
    - General, 1952-1979 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - League of Russian Veterans, subsidies, 1958-1967 (Folder 5: 2)
    - Oppression of religion in the USSR, 1961 (Folder 5: 3)
      Includes correspondence and resolution
    - Petition to free families of Agatov and Soitu from the USSR, 1975 (Folder 5: 4)
      Includes correspondence
    - Chasovoi (Watchman) magazine, materials on financial hardship of publication and distribution, 1974-1981 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Kidnapping in Paris of Russian Generals Evgenii Miller and Aleksandr Kutepov, 1937-1962. (Folder 5: 6-8)
    Includes correspondence and testimonials
- Publications, 1945-1982.
  Booklets, reports, information bulletins, press releases, and surveys, arranged chronologically by physical form
  - General
    - Russkii korpus (Russian Corps), promotion booklet, undated (Folder 5: 9)
    - Za prava i svobodu v Rossii, (For the Rights and Freedom in Russia), undated. (Folder 5: 10)
      Printed matter
    - Kto on? (Who is He?), undated (Folder 5: 11)
    - Baikalov, A. V., Programma meropriiatii na perekhodnyi period – v poriadke obsuzhdeniia (Program of Action for the Transition Period – as a matter of discussion), undated (Folder 5: 12)
    - Likhnovskii, Duke, Kto viniovnik voiny 1914 goda? (Who is responsible for the War of 1914?), undated (Folder 5: 13)
    - George, Thomas, Decision Will be in Asia, excerpts from his book, translated into Russian, undated. (Folder 5: 14)
      Typescript
    - Arian, A., Le Problème Ukrainien, undated (Folder 5: 15)
    - White, William L., Reportage sur les Russes (Report on the Russians, unique revelation of life in the Soviet Union, The Reader's Digest, 1945 February (Folder 5: 16)
    - Press releases, 1956-1970 (Folder 5: 17)
    - Vestnik Rossiiskogo Natsional'nogo Ob'edineniia v SHvetsii (Bulletin of the Russian National League in Sweden), Stockholm, 1957, number 16 (Folder 5: 18)
    - Cinquante ans de communisme en Russie, 1917-1967, èditè par Comitè de l'Emigration Nationale Russe en Belgique (Folder 5: 19)
    - 100e anniversaire de la naissance de Lenine, publiè par le Comitè de l'Emigration Nationale Russe en Belgique, 1970 (Folder 5: 20)
  - Sviaz' (Connection), monthly bulletin of Russian workers in Belgium
    - 1949 (Folder 5: 21)
      number 1, December
    - 1950 (Folder 5: 22)
      number 2-8; number 1-3
    - 1951 (Folder 5: 23)
      number 4-14
    - 1952. (Folder 5: 24)
      number 15-26 Includes two special issues on the Congress of the Russian National League
    - 1953 (Box-folder 6: 1)
      number 27-36
    - 1954 (Folder 6: 2)
      number 37-46
    - 1955 (Folder 6: 3)
      number 47-55
    - 1956 (Folder 6: 4)
      number 56-65
    - 1957 (Folder 6: 5)
      number 66-71
    - 1958 (Folder 6: 6)
      number 72-79
    - 1959 (Folder 6: 7)
      number 80-87
    - 1960 (Folder 6: 8)
      number 88-95
    - 1961 (Folder 6: 9)
      number 96-105
    - 1962 (Folder 6: 10)
      number 106-114
    - 1963 (Folder 6: 11)
      number 116-121
    - 1964 (Folder 6: 12)
      number 122-133
    - 1965 (Folder 6: 13)
      number 134-142
    - 1966 (Folder 6: 14)
      number 143-152
    - 1967 (Folder 6: 15)
      number 153-163
    - 1968 (Folder 6: 16)
      number 164-175
    - 1969 (Folder 6: 17)
      number 176-184
    - 1970 (Folder 6: 18)
      number 185-195
    - 1971 (Folder 6: 19)
      number 196-204
    - 1972 (Folder 6: 20)
      number 205-216
    - 1973 (Folder 6: 21)
      number 217-228
    - 1974 (Folder 6: 22)
      number 229-240
    - 1975 (Folder 6: 23)
      number 241-252
    - 1976 (Folder 6: 24)
      number 255-260
    - 1977 (Folder 6: 25)
      number 261-266
    - 1978 (Folder 6: 26)
      number 269-273
    - 1979 (Folder 6: 27)
      number 274-280
    - 1980 (Folder 6: 28)
      number 281-290
    - 1981 (Folder 6: 29)
      number 291-296
    - 1982 (Folder 6: 30)
      Number 297, January-February
  - Bulletin of the Russian National League in Japan, 1957 (Folder 6: 31)
  - Information Bulletin of the Russian National League in Great Britain, 1956-1957. (Folder 6: 32)
    Includes statute and news
- Radio broadcasts, Russian section, Spanish radio, Madrid, 1937; 1961 (Folder 6: 33)
- Printed matter, 1926-1980. (Box 7)
  Newspapers, newspaper clippings, and scrapbooks, arranged by physical form
  - Newspapers. Raduga (Rainbow), Brussels (Belgium), 1946, numbers 1-8. (Folder 7: 1)
  - Clippings.
    Includes two scrapbooks
    - 1926-1927 (Folder 7: 2)
    - 1937-1965 (Folder 7: 3)
    - 1952 (Folder 7: 4)
    - 1954-1955, 1977. (Folder 7: 5)
    - 1959-1964 (Folder 7: 6)
    - 1970 (Folder 7: 7)
    - 1979-1980 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Scrapbooks
      - undated (Folder 7: 9)
      - 1956-1957 (Folder 7: 10)
- Cultural life of the Russian émigré community in Belgium, 1949-1979.
  Concert programs, advertisements, leaflets, invitations, arranged chronologically by physical form
  - General. Concert programs, advertisements, leaflets, invitations, 1949-1962 (Folder 7: 11)
  - Russian opera performance, 1951 October 16 (Folder 7: 12)
  - Russian book exhibits, Brussels
    - 1972-1973. (Folder 7: 13)
      Includes extensive correspondence
    - 1973 December 14-16 (Folder 7: 14)
    - 1977 November 18-20 (Folder 7: 15)
    - 1979 December 14-16 (Folder 7: 16)
- Photographs, 1939-1956
  - Russian National League member's portraits, 5 prints, undated
  - Russian émigrés' group portraits, 7 prints, undated.
    2 of them dated 1949
  - Russian house in Brussels (Belgium), 2 prints, undated
  - Monument to the unknown soldier, 4 prints, undated
  - Memorial services to the Russian soldiers, 4 prints, undated
  - First Congress of the Russian National League, 3 prints, 1951
  - Second Congress of the Russian National League, 2 prints, 1956
  - Children's life in the Russian émigré community, 5 prints, undated
  - Russian soldiers in Spanish Army of General Franko, 2 prints, circa late 1930th
  - Finno-Russian War, scenes from, 4 prints, 1939
- Miscellany (Financial records), 1955-1977
- Oversize box, undated (Box 8)
  - Fabric banners
    - No one has the right to excuse you from executing your duty to the Motherland, undated
    - Only in fighting do we obtain our freedom, undated
  - Russian book exhibits, advertisements, undated